I like to think I'm a nice guy, but I
can be an [__]
And sometimes you have to be an [__]
especially in prison where it's a
combination of seventh grade lord of the
flies and a mental institution.
So there was a serial killer in the unit
who we called truck and he loved. So
he'd pick them up and sex with them in
the cab of his truck, but he didn't want
to pay them so he would strangle them.
and he strangled one and thought she was
dead and threw her out of the truck, but
she lived
>> and she was able to identify him. So
they knew that he was the serial killer,
but they couldn't prove it. So only the
only thing they got him on was
kidnapping, assault. So I'm sitting this
close to Cat in the Hat, sitting
directly next to a truck and not knowing
that I'm 3 feet behind him. Cat in the
head says, "Did you hear Kiryaku was
sent to the or called to the
lieutenant's office?" "That guy's a
rat," he says. And I just sat there and
truck says, "That guy just called you a
rat."
And I thought, "Here's my opportunity."
And I said, "An hour ago, I heard him
call you a ch
child."
>> Mhm.
>> He didn't say a word. He stood up, walks
over to Cat in the Hat, and beat him to
within an inch of his life. At the first
sign of trouble, everybody runs back to
the cell cuz they didn't see anything,
right?
>> They just sat there watching the
football game. So, next thing you know,
you know,
you hear the horn going off. I get up. I
casually walk back to my cell. Then they
have lockdown. Then they have to bring
medics to come and clean up Cat in the
Hats from everywhere. And uh sure
enough, I get called down to the
lieutenant's office. The lieutenant
says, "So tell me about the fight." I
said, "There was a fight?"
He said, "Oh, you're going to play it
like that, are you?" I said, "I don't
know what you're talking about. I was
watching a football game and then I
heard the alarm go off." So I went back
to my my cell and you didn't see the
fight three three feet away from you. I
said, "I didn't see any fight." I said,
"Maybe you were in a fight, huh? Why
don't you tell me about the fight? What?
You want me to do youring job for you
now, too?" He goes, "Get the [__] out of
my office." Admit nothing. Deny
everything. Make counter accusations.
[Music]
Leave them alone. What they going to say
with
[Music]
Welcome to part two of the John Kuryaku
interview. If you missed part one, I
encourage you to click the link in the
description and scope it out. No need to
see it necessarily in order, but it's an
amazing experience listening to this man
tell stories. John is an ex CIA officer,
famous in particular for his work after
9/11 and during 911 and ultimately for
his whistleblowing on the 9/11
interrogation program that the
government permitted to happen. And he
went to prison for a couple of years for
that. And we talk in depth in this
episode about his prison experience, the
CIA tactics that he leveraged in a
crooked prison system and prison reform
ideas, uh, racial divides and and how
this country can improve the processes
that we have. So that among many other
periphery things I think you're going to
truly enjoy. I consider him now a
friend. So please help me in welcoming
back to the Tegan Broadwater podcast,
Mr. John Kuryaku. Forgive me for being a
little more sporadic today because the
last time we got into a lot of stuff
that I want to get into. I also want I I
not only want to feed my audience with
some of the the stories that we missed,
but I also want to get into some things
that I really care about in terms of uh
the experience in prison, which we
didn't really get to talk about.
>> Yeah, we didn't touch that. We really
didn't get a good opportunity to explain
how prison even occurred which was very
unfair because you know you get some of
those comments that are either
uneducated or guessing and and I I hated
that also. So I think that that's and
the book is great doing time like a spy
is a great book too for anybody that
wants to buy a book and get some good
reading in. But
>> I thought I would jump back kind of to
the beginning and see if we could launch
this way. So you had mentioned before
that both of your parents were teachers.
Your mother went back, got a master's
degree and everything else. So obviously
you grew up in a household where that
was how you were weaned.
>> Mhm.
With all the training that you had in
the CIA and all the circumstances you
had to mitigate, was there ever a time
like an epiphany or something where you
either
had a survival skill develop or handled
something under pressure or had an
opportunity to read somebody where you
attributed that skill back to something
you learned as a kid from your mother as
opposed to something you were taught,
something more inherent, a situation you
were in.
>> Wow, that's a good question. That's a
hard question.
>> Well, I didn't mean it to be hard
necessarily, but
>> Well, on the one hand, the training at
the CIA is unbelievably thorough,
>> right?
>> On the other hand,
your mind has to be adaptable to it or
you're going to fail.
>> And you also have to be in a position to
be selected, which also means you have a
disposition that they also want.
>> But that's nature.
>> It is. And so some of that has to be I'm
just curious about how much of that is
>> something that was put into you where
you leveraged it.
>> You know, I think I would say that it
was actually the opposite where
nothing from my childhood was directly
applicable
to what I ended up doing in the CIA.
Let me rephrase.
Nothing that came out of nurture
was applicable. It was nature that was
applicable. Um with with one exception,
I was always the good cop. That's a part
of my nature. I like people. I like
talking. I like exchanging stories and
ideas and hanging out. I get I I feel
like I gain strength by being around
other people.
>> Mhm. And when you're trying to recruit
somebody, when you're trying to convince
somebody to commit treason for you or
espionage for you just cuz you're a good
guy,
you sort of need that, right?
>> Yeah.
>> It was never my nature to say, you know,
give me the information or I'm going to
break your nose. I'm going to tear off
your arm and beat you to death with it.
That's
I don't find that to be a useful
strategy.
And I was raised in a very warm, loving
nuclear household.
So I had that as a basis. But in terms
of the actual spy craft
>> Mhm.
>> that was all taught.
>> Okay. Well, that that's interesting
enough. I mean, that says a lot about
that training program, too. Yeah.
>> This is not a way that people think
naturally. You know, I've I've said
before that the CIA actively seeks to
hire people who have sociopathic
tendencies,
>> not sociopaths, because sociopaths have
no conscience, and they're impossible to
control. They blow right through a
polygraph because they don't feel guilt
or remorse.
>> Right?
>> People who have sociopathic tendencies
do feel remorse, but are happy to break
the law because we're the good guys and
it's all about the end result.
>> For the cause, you're willing.
>> It's for the cause. Yeah,
>> God and country. Um, and in in
retrospect, I have or had sociopathic
tendencies. For example, and stop me if
I told you this already, but when I was
going through the application process, I
had been recommended by my grad school
adviser, so I didn't like physically
apply. So, I'm in this this group
setting with three or four other
applicants, and the uh the proctor says,
"You're a CIA officer overseas. You get
a cable from headquarters telling you
that headquarters really needs the
latest Indonesian economic figures,
and
you have to go get it. So, go." What do
you do? Well, you seek out the
Indonesian economic secretary at the
embassy. You start working him, take him
to lunch, take him to dinner. He
mentions he likes fishing. You charter a
boat. You go deep sea fishing. You get
your wives together. You have them over
to your house. Maybe you go away for the
weekend. You become great friends. But 6
months into it, you realize he's just
not recruitable. So then what do you do?
And this guy raises his hand and he
says, "Well, you double down. You go
another 6 months. You spend more money
on him." This woman raises her hand. She
says, "Maybe you work it through the
wives. Maybe the wives become closer."
And I'm looking around like, "What?" I
raised my hand. I said, "You break into
the embassy and you steal it." And the
guy goes, "That's exactly what you do."
That's a sociopathic tendency. A normal
person
won't default to breaking into a foreign
embassy and stealing classified dollars.
>> The last thing that comes to a normal
person's mind,
>> right? It was the first thing that came
to my mind.
>> Hey, if you're like me and you are
frustrated sometimes about ways that you
can make a positive impact, I can tell
you that one of the simplest things that
you can do that goes such a long way is
to like and subscribe to this channel
and share some of these videos that
you're enjoying. It brings other people
into the middle regardless of their
perspective to start engaging into that
productive conversation that we all
need. Thanks in advance.
>> So that's a tendency.
>> That's great. And you look at things
backwards often when you're assessing a
target or whatever. You kind of think of
worst case scenarios or how would I do
it if
>> you find yourself doing that.
>> If I do it this way, is the guy going to
shoot me in the face
>> or is he going to say, "Oh, let's have a
beer."
It's kind of an important Yeah.
distinction.
>> It's exactly right.
>> So, you talk about recruiting. Uh, have
you ever has anyone ever tried to flip
you or recruit you in the past? Yeah.
>> And how did you how did you navigate
that?
>> Well, the first time
I didn't even realize it was happening.
And uh and I got to thinking about it
later. I there's no harm in saying who
it was. It was a Hungarian uh
intelligence officer.
And so I reported it and I said, you
know, this is probably nothing, but I
just wanted to be on the safe side. So I
reported it and then headquarters came
back and said, "Oh no, he's an
identified intelligence officer. Good
for reporting it." So I just stayed away
from him. Then there was one time where
I had to I was assigned to work with
this French idiot from the French
intelligence service and I called him
and I said, "Okay, so we're supposed to
do this thing together. Where do you
want to meet?" He said, "Well, meet me
at the corner of, you know, A and B." I
thought that was odd, but okay. So I
meet I'm standing there at the corner of
A and B. He comes down this alley, makes
a right turn, and he's like, "Get in. We
only have 15 seconds." And I'm like,
"No, no, no, no. I'm not a clandestine
source of yours. I'm not going to take
the 15-second window to jump in your car
if you haven't done the surveillance
detection route. I'm just going to meet
you at the Pizza Hut and we're going to
have our meeting there. But I'm not
doing this clandestine game thing with
you. No. And afterwards, I wrote
headquarters. I was like, tell the
French that they need to change their MO
because I'm not doing this with this
guy.
>> So, it was that it was that apparent
though.
>> Yeah. I was ridiculous. Ridiculous. But
then there were there were times where I
expected a pitch that never came. I
expected the Greeks to pitch me. Never
even a hint. I expected the Russians at
some point. Nothing at all. So, you just
never know. Sometimes you're just a
target of opportunity for for an odd
outline ser service. Let me say one
other thing, too.
>> Mhm. Um, when I was senior staff member
on the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee, I was there from 2009 to
midway through 2011. I was the chief
investigator
and uh I got a call from a Japanese
diplomat who said, "Hey, let's uh let's
go to lunch." I said, "Great. I love
doing this. I love going out with
foreign diplomats and just talking about
whatever happens to be in the news." And
>> it's post CIA at this time.
>> PostCIA.
So,
we go out to this steakhouse and
perfectly delightful lunch. I remember
what we talked about. We talked about
the Middle East peace process, Israeli
elections, and Turkish elections.
And at the end of it, I said, "Well,
thank you for meeting me. This was a a
lovely lunch." And he said, "No, no, no.
Before you leave," he said, "Uh, what's
next for you?" And I should add his
English was so bad that we did the lunch
in Arabic. He was an Arabist. Yeah.
>> So I said, "Well, I think I'm going to
resign soon." I promised Senator Kerry,
it was John Ky was the chairman at the
time. I promised Senator Kerry I'd give
him two years. It's been two and a half.
I have five kids. I still have to put
three through college. So I said, "I I
need to make some money." And he goes,
"Don't resign.
if you give me information, I can give
you money.
And I said, "What is wrong with you? How
dare you cold pitch me like that? Do you
have any idea how many times I've made
that pitch? Shame on you," I said. And I
got up and I walked out and I went
directly without stopping to the office
of the Senate Security Officer. So, I go
in there and I said, "I was just pitched
by a foreign intelligence officer." And
he said, "Was it that damn Russian
again?" And I said, "No, Japanese." He
goes, "Japanese?"
I said, "Yeah, I know. I'm shocked,
too." And he said, "Well, you know, the
Japanese poke around every once in a
while on trade issues." I said, "This
was a direct cold pitch,
>> right? Nothing subtle about
>> nothing subtle at all. No room for
confusion."
>> So, he says, "Write it up on this
standalone computer that's not connected
to the internet, and I'll send it to the
FBI." So, I wrote it up. He sends it to
the FBI. The next day he calls me. He
says, "Two FBI agents want to come up
and interview you." I said, "Okay,
great." I meet them in the skiff. The
next the secure uh skiff secure
conference uh or no, special
compartmented information, whatever.
It's a secure conference room.
>> Got it.
>> So, um
these two young guys come up and they
said, "Here's what we want you to do. we
want you to invite him to lunch and try
to get him to tell you exactly what
information he wants and how much money
he's willing to pay for it. And I said,
"Okay, you want me to wear a wire or
something?" They said, "No, no, we're
going to be at the next table. We'll
we'll listen to everything." I said,
"Okay." So, I invite him to lunch.
He lays it all out. These guys had
called me right before the meeting,
said, "Something came up. We can't do
it. Just write up another memo." I
thought that was odd. But okay, I write
the memo. I send it. And I I always
prided myself on my accounts of my
meetings. They're very wholesome.
>> So then they asked me to do it a third
meeting, a fourth meeting, a fifth
meeting.
>> Were they showing up at these or
>> just write them up? So I'm writing every
detail. He said this, I said that. He
did this, I did that. Back and forth
like you're in the room.
So, at the last meeting, it was at a
restaurant in Georgetown. He says to me,
"I just got promoted, got my dream job.
I'm going to be the number two at the
Japanese embassy in Cairo." I said,
"Congratulations." Never saw him again.
A year later, I get arrested after
blowing the whistle on the program. And
we get 15,000 pages of classified
discovery.
And it turns out, we get these memos
that there was no Japanese diplomat. He
was an FBI agent pretending to be a
Japanese diplomat.
And
they did five meetings with me because I
kept reporting the contact back to the
Japanese, I mean to the FBI,
>> right?
>> And so finally he writes, "He's clearly
not going to take the the bait. Suggest
we end this operation." They were trying
to get me to commit actual espionage
because they wanted to charge me with
espionage.
>> But what did they what did they think
you were going to give up? This is the
You'd already by this time you'd gone on
television and talked about the 9/11
programs that they thought you were just
somebody that was just going to
>> vomit a bunch of stuff.
>> Yeah. Uh-huh.
>> And anything. They were just fishing for
anything.
>> Anything. Anything. They could charge me
with a crime. And uh and I never gave
them anything. And I kept reporting the
contact back.
So, do you think that has anything to do
with how they ended up charging you? Can
you go into detail a little bit more
just to to kind of give us a little
background into what you were charged
with and and and how that kind of
unfolded? Cuz I know last time we talked
specifically about
>> the interview you went on and that
>> some of that stuff you thought was
public information already. It wasn't
like I'm gonna go on this show and I'm
gonna out everything. No,
>> you were quite upset about the 9/11
program.
>> Yeah, I was.
>> But it wasn't necessarily an intentional
thing where you were bound and
determined to let it out.
>> No. No. So, I said three things in that
interview. This was an interview with
ABC News and a subsequent interview with
the New York Times. I said that the CIA
wasing its prisoners, which was illegal.
I said that there was official US
government policy, also illegal. And I
said that the policy had been personally
approved by the president himself, which
he had denied and denied and denied and
then admitted.
So they charged me with three counts of
espionage for speaking to ABC News and
the New York Times. They charged me with
one count of um violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of 1982.
And they charged me with making a false
statement. We were never clear on
exactly what the false statement was
supposed to have been.
But they knew that those espionage
charges were were made up. There was
there was a memo from John Brennan in
Discovery to Eric Holder who was the
attorney general and he said, "Charge
him with espionage." And Eric Holder
wrote back and said, "My people don't
think he committed espionage." And then
Brennan wrote back and said, "Charge him
anyway and make him defend himself." So
they charged me with three counts of
espionage. This is a death penalty
charge.
They charged me three counts
and then when I went bankrupt, they
dropped the charges.
See, so what they were hoping was that I
would actually tell this pretend
Japanese diplomat something that wasn't
public so they could charge me with
actual espionage.
>> Right. So that was tied in directly to
cuz you by that time they were looking
to charge you in other words.
>> Yeah. And so they were trying to
substantiate the charges that they had
out there because otherwise the FBI was
thinking there really isn't anything
here.
>> Yeah, there's nothing there wise,
>> right?
>> That's insane. So, how does it feel? I I
I can only imagine how it would feel for
you knowing damn well that you're
innocent of these charges that you've
been that have been laid upon you, but
you take a plea deal.
>> Mhm. So, and in some states it's not
even legal to take a plea deal and say,
"I plead guilty to this even though I
don't think that I did it."
>> Well, I stood up in court. We negotiated
the deal, right? I had I was facing 45
years. That was their offer was 45
years.
>> And then
I offered to take a plea to one count
for 23 months. The 30 months I would do
23 months. And so I stood up in court
and the judge said, "Uh, have you agreed
to this plea deal?" I said, "Yes." "Are
you actually guilty of the crime?" And I
said, "No." And then she says, "Mr.
Cateris, you might want to talk to your
client." And then he says, "You have to
say you're guilty." I said, "But I'm not
guilty. I just want the deal." He said,
"You have to say that you're guilty."
And I said, "Sure, I'm guilty."
>> So, how did that feel? I mean, it's got
to be
>> The whole system is perverted.
>> Yeah. The whole system, you know,
there's this joke that everybody in
prison's innocent. I was shocked at the
number of people in prison that were
innocent.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Because they stack these charges on you.
They'll charge you with 20 felonies. And
then at the end when you're beaten down,
they say, "All right, we'll dismiss 19
of them if you take a guilty plea of the
one. Do 5 years." What are you going to
do? You're facing 300 years in prison.
>> Yeah. But that's different, though.
That's different if you're guilty of the
one,
>> right?
>> If you're not guilty of 20 and they're
just playing that chess game and saying,
"We're going to charge you with 20 and
come down." But you're actually,
you know, a dealer, a supplier, a
conspirator or whatever.
>> But the feds win 98.2%
of their cases according to ProPublica.
98.2. So, do you really want to roll
those dice knowing that you have a 1.8%
chance of winning? I said to my
attorneys, "Well, I'm I'm getting ahead
of myself." They made their best and
final offer. 30 months, I do 23. And I
had until noon the next day to either
accept or reject. My wife and I stayed
up all night long.
And we decided, I'm going to turn it
down. I hadn't done anything wrong. As
soon as I got in front of a jury, I
said, "They're going to see how
ridiculous this is," which was
ridiculous in and of itself. to even
think that.
>> Right.
>> So, I emailed the lawyers at 6 a.m. I
said, "We've been up all night. I'm
turning it down. Let's go to trial."
>> What was your level of emotion at that
point? No sleep, talking through it,
knowing that you're looking at
>> almost the rest of your life.
>> Yeah. It would have been the rest of
>> versus a couple of years and then you I
mean, sending that email has to be
>> It was so incredibly stressful and
nerve-wracking. So at 7:00, one of the
one of the attorneys writes back and
says, "Put on a pot of coffee. We're
coming over 7:00 in the morning." So I
had 11 lawyers. Four of them came over
to the house. The four top ones. And um
the lead attorney, Plato Cater, he's
dead now, but he was already in his mid
80s then. And he was a Washington the
the Washington Post called him a legal
titan. That's really what he what he
was.
He comes in first. He gets right in my
face and he says, "You stupid son of a
[__] Take the deal." Like that. And I
was like, "Whoa,
what's up with you? You're the one who
told me not to take a deal. You said
they had a [__] case and they know it's
[__] and we're going to trial." He said,
"I only said that to make you feel
better."
>> Yeah. So the second attorney, Bob Trout,
lovely, lovely southern gentleman, he
said to me, "If you were my own brother,
I would beg you to take this deal. Take
the deal."
>> Good way to put it.
>> Did he say, "Why?"
>> No, but the third one did.
>> Mark McDougall. I liked and respected
Mark the most out of all of them. He was
tough. In fact, several people, friends
of mine, independently of one another,
described him to me as the meanest man
in Washington.
>> And I said, "Well, I'm glad he's on my
side if he's the meanest man." I found
him to be absolutely wonderful
>> and brilliant.
And he got in my face, too. And he said,
"You know what your problem is? Your
problem is you think this is about
justice, and it's not about justice.
It's about mitigating damage. take the
deal.
>> There you go.
>> And then the fourth one, John Hunley,
I said to him, if I don't take the deal
and I'm convicted, what am I
realistically looking at? And he said,
12 to 18 years, take the deal.
And so I took it.
You know, McDougall said another thing.
He said, "Listen, this could be a blip
in your life or it can be the defining
event in your life. Make it the blip."
>> Amen to that.
>> Mhm.
>> But still, that's so easy for anyone
else to say.
>> And I went into prison with an attitude
like all of you people, not afraid of
you, and I'm not going to help you run
your prison either. You know, I'm not
going to do anything that serves the
administration. You know, clean the
clean the warden's office. Tell the
warden clean his owning office. I'm not
going to help him run his prison.
>> How much push back did you get there
versus push back from the inmates in the
collective scenario there?
>> I was very fortunate with the inmates
first. It's it's easier for me to
explain this by starting with the
inmates.
Um
you know, we have a weird system in this
country. If you're not remanded into
custody at sentencing
um on your first day of prison, you have
to just drive to the prison and knock on
the door and say, "I'm John Kuryako. I'm
here to turn myself in." It's weird. So,
the morning that I left for prison, said
goodbye to my kids and my wife, um my
attorneys, several of my attorneys, uh
came to drive me, my cousin and his son,
a documentary film crew. We stopped at a
diner on the way up for my last meal and
then uh and then we went to the prison.
So at sentencing, my attorneys asked
that I be sent to a minimum security
work camp. And there are no bars on the
windows. The doors are unlocked. You're
just on your honor not to run away. Um
and camps are always across the street
from the actual prison because if
there's a riot and a lockdown, it's the
guys in the camp who go do the cooking
and the laundry and the maintenance and
stuff like that.
>> Interesting. Okay.
>> Yeah. So, I go to the camp, knock on the
door, tell the guard I'm here to turn
myself in. He says, "Yeah, you got to go
across the street to the prison first
and they process you and then they'll
they'll bring you back over here." And I
said, "Okay." So, I went across the
street to the prison, knocked on that
door.
Cop opens the door. I said, "I'm here to
turn myself in." He puts me through the
metal detector, and then he starts
taking me around to the back of the
prison. And I said, "No, no. I'm
supposed to be at the camp across the
street." And he goes, "Not according to
my paperwork. You're not."
>> Mhm.
>> And I said to myself, "Take it easy.
There's nothing you can do. If you raise
a ruckus, they're going to put you
straight in solitary." So, I didn't say
anything.
So, they take me into R&D, receiving,
and discharge. And um
they give you a very comprehensive
um
body check
and then they give you, you know, three
pairs of underwear, three pairs of
socks, three shirts, three pants,
and uh
two sheets.
What else? A washcloth and a towel and a
roll of toilet paper.
And um it took about 40 minutes and then
the cop walks me to my cell and the only
thing he said to me in the whole 40
minutes
was
if anybody comes into your cell
uninvited that's an act of aggression.
I thought great I've been here 40
minutes and I'm going to get my ass
kicked.
I thought well all right well there's
nothing I can do. So I go into the cell.
I took a nap and I realized later it was
cuz I was in shock. I think
>> you'd been through a whole lot leading
to this time too in terms of stress.
Your body's probably ready.
>> It was just overwhelming.
>> Yeah.
>> So I wake up. I'm just sitting in the
chair. The these cells were built for
four guys, but they squeeze an extra
bunk bed in. So there's six guys in a
fourman cell. You got three bunk beds
and one plastic chair. So, I'm sitting
in the chair and these two guys just
walk right into my cell. One has a that
takes up his entire neck, the whole
front of his neck up onto his face. The
other one had you tattooed on his
eyelids. So, every time he blinked, it
said you. So, um they come into the I
know, right? Isn't that lovely?
>> He's wholesome.
>> Like, your parents must be so proud,
right? His mom didn't go back and get a
master's degree and teach him anything.
>> No. So I jump up. I put up my dukes. I I
go, "What do you want?" Like that. And
the guy goes, "Take it easy." This guy,
"Take it easy. You the new guy?" I go,
"Yeah." So he goes, "You a no I'm not a
You a You a rat?" I said, "No, I'm not a
rat. I didn't have anybody else in my
case." And he goes, "You a ch?" I said,
"I don't know what that word means." And
he goes, "Chill child." I said, "No, I'm
not a child."
And he goes, "Okay, you can sit with the
Aryans in the cafeteria." And I go, "Oh,
okay.
>> I'm so delighted to hear this."
>> And now I I'm with the Aryans. I said to
myself, "Great."
So, a couple of days later, this black
guy walks walks right into my cell and
he's holding this newspaper. And again,
I jump up and this guy is like knotted
muscled, the the a perfect human
specimen, right?
>> And I jump up and go, "What do you
want?"
>> And I'm thinking, I wouldn't last 5
seconds against
>> He's going to break me in half, but I'm
going to be swinging my arms when he
does it.
>> That's it. Hay makers. That's right.
>> So, uh,
he very gingerly hands me this paper and
I see it's the paper the newspaper of
the Nation of Islam and he said, "Are
you the CIA guy?" And I said, "Yeah."
And he says, as he hands me the paper,
he says, "Reverend Farrakhan says you're
a hero of the Muslim people and I want
you to know you won't have any problems
with us." H and I said, "Oh, okay.
Thanks."
I actually put my hand out and he's
like, "I don't shake hands with the
white devil."
I was like, "Sorry, sorry." Okay. Thank
you.
>> Getting carried away a little bit.
So,
so of my cellmates
in that original cell, four were members
of Mexican
uh cartels, the Burachos, Nortenos,
Mexican,
and I forget the other one now. And then
one Chinese drug smuggler.
And um so one of the Mexicans said to
me, "Are you are you educated?" And I
said, "Yeah." He said, "Can you write my
appeal?" And I said, "I'm not a lawyer."
Yeah, but you're educated. I said,
'Yeah, sure. I'll write your appeal. How
hard could it possibly be? The guy was
guilty. I mean, the DEA had actually
shot him. He had a bullet wound, like
the scar from the bullet where the DEA
shot him. They had like 20 tons of
cocaine in a in a warehouse in Houston,
>> right?
>> So, I wrote the appeal. The appeal was
denied, but he told all the Mexicans
that I was a good guy because I wrote
the appeal. And I didn't charge him
anything. I said, he offered me the the
currency is either books of stamps,
which were worth $7 at the time, or bags
of mackerel, smoked mackerel. Those were
worth a buck.
>> So, I said, "No, I got people on the
outside. I don't need I don't need your
Mac." So, um, he told everybody, "Oh, I
was a good guy, and I didn't charge many
money." So, I didn't have any problem
with the Mexicans either,
the Italians. And this is what made my
prison experience so easy.
There was a front page article in the
New York Times on a Sunday saying the
CIA guy is going to FCI Lorettto,
Pennsylvania on Thursday. And one
Italian, Mark Lanelotti, God bless him,
for whatever reason
took it upon himself to go to every one
of the Italians. And there were at least
a half a dozen made men. One was a boss
of one of the five families
and one was the number three in another
family.
>> And uh he went to each one of these
Italians to explain to them the
difference between a CIA officer and an
FBI agent. FBI agent is a cop.
Cop and a rat is what he said. A CIA
officer protected us from the Muslims.
And so the Italians welcomed me with
open arms. I lived directly across the
hall from the number three in the Banano
crime family. I used to give him my New
York Times. He would give me his New
York Post. We'd watch football on the
weekends.
>> And he said to me one day, "Let me ask
you something." He said, "Why do you sit
with those nasty retards in the
cafeteria?"
I said, "I don't know. They came up to
me my first day here and told me to sit
with the Aryans." and he says, "From
today, you're with the Italians."
And they adopted me and I was with the
Italians the rest of the time. And I'll
tell you, word got around quickly that I
was with the Italians. And so it was
hands off
>> really
>> cuz those were top level Italians.
>> The Italians were the very smallest one
of the groups or gangs
>> and they were the most highly respected.
Do you think a lot of that was
perception from movies and such?
>> Without any question.
>> Interesting.
>> Yeah. Without any how how much of those
people do you feel like
>> wore the perception of movies with them,
including the
Mexican mafia and all those guys? I
mean, cuz really when it gets down to
it, you know, I've had that experience
where you strip down and you're talking
about a video game or something else.
You're like, this is just a dude.
>> Just a dude. That's so true.
>> Other than it says few on his eyelids
right now.
>> Plus, think of it this way. This was a
low security prison. Not a minimum, but
a low. So, it goes maximum, medium, low,
minimum. Most of these guys started off
at a maximum. And because of good
behavior, they work their way down to a
low. They don't want to go back up to a
medium or maximum. So, they're not going
to make any trouble. There were like
three fights the whole two years I was
there. And all three of the fights were
about what to watch on TV.
>> That sounds like uh they were married
before.
>> Oh my god. The Hispanics control half
the TVs and the blacks control the other
half. The whites don't get a choice. So
you just you can choose to watch, you
know, Love and Hip Hop Atlanta or the
the Costa Rica versus Venezuela soccer
match.
>> Other than that, you're [__] out of
luck. find it fascinating that you
ironically in in some way leveraged your
CIA training there to help people
genuinely helping people.
>> Mhm.
>> Um it did
>> beat the government who essentially put
them there.
>> Oh, the best the best experience that I
had in that respect was my friend Mark
Lanzotti. Mark was my best friend in
prison and remains one of my best
friends post prison over the last 10
years. He's a genuinely sweet, good,
kind person who never should have been
in prison in the very first place. But
toward the end of my sentence,
Obama passed the uh was it called the
first step, the act or something like
that? Second chance act. I can't
remember. Anyway, I'm sitting in Mark's
cell and I'm reading the New York Times.
No, it wasn't the New York Times. It was
USA Today that Mark used to get. And I
said, "Buddy, did you read this
article?" And he said, "No." I said,
"This article is about you. It's about
people who have ridiculously long
sentences that if they were tried today
and convicted, they would get shorter
sentences." And you have to have had no
gun involved in the in the case and no
gang affiliation.
So,
just as background, Mark had a
stepfather years and years ago who made
meth and he brought Mark and like eight
other guys, five other guys, whatever it
was, into this meth manufacturing
>> plan.
Mark decided this wasn't for him and he
quit. He was the only person to
voluntarily leave the conspiracy. Sure
enough, a couple of years later, they
all get wrapped wrapped up by DEA
and
they all want to flip. So Mark's the
only one not arrested. Well, to flip,
they point the finger at each other.
They point the finger at Mark. Mark's
stepfather says, "I'll pay for your
lawyer if you don't take a plea cuz I
don't pay for rats." Mark had no idea
everybody else was ratting him out.
>> Right. Always the case. So they all got
5 and a/4 years. Mark got triple life
without parole.
>> Oh my gosh.
>> For a first time nonviolent drug offense
and he was the only one to leave the
conspiracy.
So they sent him to the maximum security
penitentiary at Springfield.
>> It was such an extraordinary sentence.
They figured this guy's a mobster.
>> Mobster.
>> Ridiculous.
>> Yeah. He actually uh developed bone
cancer and because he was deemed to be
such a dangerous threat to society,
he had surgery to remove the cancerous
bone in his wrist in the parking lot of
the prison in a motor home that they
converted into a surgical unit.
>> None of this none of this had behavior
manifest in prison and they still treat
it like that. like they just for a meth
dealer
>> they don't care. They don't care.
>> Ridiculous though.
>> He appealed and they reduced his
sentence to 30 years.
>> Hey, if you're like me and you are
frustrated sometimes about ways that you
can make a positive impact, I can tell
you that one of the simplest things that
you can do that goes such a long way is
to like and subscribe to this channel
and share some of these videos that
you're enjoying. It brings other people
into the middle, regardless of their
perspective, to start engaging into that
productive conversation that we all
need. Thanks. in advance.
>> So, he was at the halfway point when I
met him. So, I'm reading the USA Today.
I said I said, "Buddy, they're talking
about you in this article." And he said,
"Yeah, but I don't even know how I'd go
about applying for relief. I don't know
what to do." I said, "I'm going to write
it." So, I went to the law library, took
an exemplar, cuz I'm not a lawyer, but
most lawyers are morons anyway.
Seriously. So I was like, I can do this.
So I wrote an appeal and I sent it. Then
I got released.
So I'm I'm out of prison. Let me think
6 months and Mark's mom calls me and I
see it's her and I I answer the phone. I
said, "Hi, Ro." She's bawling. I said,
"Oh my god, what happened?" I thought
something terrible. He got killed in
prison.
>> Yeah. And she said, "Um, Mark's being
released." And I said, "What?" And she
said, "Your appeal that you wrote, he
won. He's being released.
>> He got commuted."
>> Mhm. Man, see, no wonder you're best
friends. You be my best friend, too.
That's unbelievable.
>> He took such good care of me in prison.
You know, I I'm I'm sure you saw in the
book Mark
Mark had a gift for the most wonderful
Italian cooking I've ever experienced in
my life.
He would he would take a garbage can
and put a plastic bag in it. Fill the
plastic bag with water,
plug a live wire into the wall with, you
know, the the pieces of the wire coming
out the other end.
>> Split.
>> Yeah. Split. Throw it in the water. It
goes and the water starts boiling. And
then he has all this other stuff in
another bag and he puts it in the
boiling water. The Italians had a
crooked cop on the payroll. So he'd
bring in, you know, pork loin and ve and
the crusty bread and mushrooms and
tomatoes and white wine for the Marsala
sauce. I gained 35 lbs in prison.
>> I said to him one day, I said, I would
spend $50 on this in a restaurant.
That's how good it was. Every single day
we had dinner together, all the
Italians. Every single.
>> Is he a restaurant tour now? You know,
crazy thing. He got out of prison and I
said, "Tell me you're going to open a
restaurant." And he said, "I think I'm
going to apply for a real estate
license." And I said, "Yeah, but you're
a felon, so you you can't be licensed."
He writes a letter to to Chris Christie
when he was a governor, and he said,
"Look, you know, I I did this crime. I
took responsibility for it. I got
commuted by President Obama because
Justice Department screwed me. I want to
rebuild my life. Would you please lift
the ban on uh my ability to get a real
estate license? And he did.
>> All you had to do was ask.
>> All he had to do was ask.
>> Who knew?
>> And so he passes the exam for the real
estate license. And now, and I'm not
exaggerating, he is the number one
selling realtor on the Jersey Shore.
>> Welld deserved.
>> Number one. That's He could have written
his own commutation request then.
Perhaps
>> he probably should should have.
>> But you're a smart guy. I mean, you're
not the average smart guy. You're a very
smart guy. I think it's I think it's
also quite genuinely noble of you to
have done things like that. That's
>> you don't you don't hear as many stories
like that as you do, you know, that you
know, whoever can street fight the best
or intimidate somebody. Yeah. Yeah.
>> And I do know that you had to leverage.
I mean, you make it sound kind of like a
cakewalk, but I read the book, so I know
there's more than cakewalking.
>> Yeah.
>> And certainly the, you know, the process
leading up to it, I know, was was
traumatic. So, what were some of the
things that you did leverage
>> without going into an exhaustive list?
And I know maybe even some things you
you aren't proud of now.
>> Maybe maybe introduction to the book.
Maybe any anything that you feel like uh
you know I just I've been inclined to to
to think what is something that you did
there is where I think there would be
more things but it could possibly be in
the CIA too something that you've done
that that you weren't proud of
necessarily but was kind of a slick
move. You know, in the book I I have
these 20 life lessons that the CIA
taught me, and some of them I started
writing that book sort of as a comedy,
>> but I realized as I was writing it,
>> no, this is this is real.
>> Yeah. It's just the tone.
>> It's not at all funny.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you know, I'd say things like, "Oh,
the CIA said, uh, admit nothing, deny
everything, make counter accusations."
Haha. And I actually used that against
the cops a couple of times, but there
were a couple things in there that were
serious like make others do your dirty
work or um
oh my gosh, there were so there were so
many um you know I talked about
trickery. So in in the introduction to
the book I say
people say I'm a nice guy. I like to
think I'm a nice guy, but I can be an
[__] And sometimes you have to be an
[__] especially in prison where it's
a combination of seventh grade, Lord of
the Flies, and a mental institution,
which is true.
>> Perfect.
>> So,
in the introduction of the book, I say I
talk about this guy that I call Wallace
in the book. It's It's not hard to
figure out who it is, but this guy had
gone out with an A-list Hollywood star,
an Academy Award winner, household name.
And he was just a con man, right? He was
just a fraudster. He would steal her
money and steal her friends money. And
he got caught. He went to prison. His
father went to prison. They were just
common conmen.
>> Yep.
>> This guy never shut his mouth 24 hours a
day. the whole time. And so I said to
one of the Italians one day, I said,
"I'm this guy up. I've had enough." And
he goes, "Are you crazy? You're going to
go straight to solitary and you're going
to be in there for 6 weeks and then
they're going to send you another
prison." I said, "I would never be so
crude as to physically him up."
I said, "Watch and see what I do."
>> You underestimate me, sir.
>> Yes, you underestimate me, sir.
So,
oh, this guy. I won't get into the
background, but oh my god, I hated this
guy so much. So, when you're being
released from prison, they give you a
sheet of paper called a merrygoround.
And all it is is it's got a list of all
the offices in the prison, and you have
to go get a signature on your last full
day. You don't need any signatures for
real. It's just to keep you out of
trouble that last day so you're not out
there settling scores before you leave.
So,
one of the Mexicans in my cell was
getting released and I said, "Jose, can
I borrow your uh your merrygoround?" He
said, "Sure." So, I take it up to the
library. I make a photo copy. I white
out's name and prisoner number. I make a
clean copy. I type in Wallace's name and
number. Give Jose back his original.
Then one of the Italians, I asked him to
steal the laundry bag. Gives me the
laundry bag. I wait until 5:00 on a
Friday. I put the merrygoround on
Wallace's bed and the empty uh
>> laundry bag.
>> Laundry bag. So Wallace comes in like,
"Hey guys. Hey Wallace." He goes over to
his bed. He goes
I said what? He goes, "I'm going home."
I said, "What?
It's a merrygoround. I'm going home." He
goes, "I must have won my appeal. Nobody
wins their appeal. I won." I go, "Oh my
god, Wallace, congratulations." The
Italian says, "Wallace, let us have a
party for you tomorrow night. We'll have
a big party." He's like, "I got to call
my lawyer." He runs to the phones. Well,
even fancy New York lawyers are gone by
six o'clock on a Friday afternoon,
>> right?
>> He goes to the unit manager. He's long
gone. He goes to the case manager. He
was gone at 2:00.
So, I said, "Wallace, we got to
celebrate all weekend.
This
>> is terrible."
>> So, he gives away all of his possessions
cuz he doesn't need them anymore. He's
going home. So, we have this big going
away party, big dinner. Saturday night,
Sunday, he's going around shaking hands
with everybody. Goodbye. Goodbye.
Goodbye. Monday morning, we all walk him
down to receiving and discharge. So
long, Wallace. Good luck, buddy. And
he's like, "You're all going to come on
my yacht. When you get out, we're going
to cruise the Mediterranean." We're
like, "Thank you, Wallace."
The cop in R&D later told us the rest of
the story. Wallace goes into R&D. The
cop says, "Who are you?" He says, "I'm
Wallace. What are you doing here?" "I'm
going home." He hands him the
merrygoround. Cop looks at the
merrygoround. He says, "Turn around.
You're under arrest for what?" Attempted
escape.
And they cuff him. He bursts into tears.
They take him to solitary. He's in there
for 6 weeks and then they send him to a
prison in Ohio for the rest of his term.
They did not charge him with attempted
escape. They didn't charge him with
anything because they actually believed
him when he said that he really believed
he was being released.
>> Right. He got punked.
>> He got punked.
>> Yeah.
>> And nobody knew who did it.
>> And ultimately you got him out of your
hair.
>> I did. And so
a very senior captain in the Banano
family came up to me and said, "I can't
believe you pulled that off." I said, "I
told you I was going to him up and now
he's gone. Gone and done."
>> That's remarkable.
>> Well, there was a there was a story
that's not so fun. Um, there was a you
know, when you have an empty uh bunk in
your in your cell,
it's a very big deal.
So, if you've got a good cell, got all
good guys and and my second cell was all
good guys. We had planned it very well.
Um, people line up to sort of apply for
the bunk and the the case manager who's
who's in charge of uh bunk assignments
will ask, "Have you cleared this with
the other guys in the cell?" Otherwise,
you're going to get a beatdown.
>> Mhm.
So
we interviewed people like, "Oh, you
want to be in our cell? Okay, you're
child get the out. We don't have
childers in this cell." Then there was
one guy, he was relatively new from
Pittsburgh. We called him the Cat in the
Hat cuz he had this unusually elongated
head like you could project a movie on
his forehead, you know, and he looked
like the Cat in the Hat.
So the Cat in the Hat comes and he says
he wants to move into our cell. And I
said, "Well, what's what's your crime?
Are you a ch?" He said, "No, I'm not a
ch" I said, "What's your crime?" He
said, "For hire." And I said, "Ooh, I'm
not sure I like that one either." I
said, "Well, what were the
circumstances?" and he said, 'Well, I uh
I had a gambling problem and I uh I was
a h 100red grand in debt to the mafia
and I couldn't pay it. So, I took out a
$100,000 life insurance policy on my
business partner and I hired a hitman to
uh to hit him and the hitman hit him and
then got arrested and ratted me out. But
then the hitman had a heart attack and
died in prison and I had already taken a
plea so I got 20 years.
I said, "I that's not cool. So, you're a
rat. You ratted out the hitman." And he
said, "Yeah, we ratted each other out."
I said, "No, no, no rats." I told him in
our cell.
So,
>> it's got to be hard to find somebody
that's not a rat in federal prison
>> because the all that's left is the
Aryans.
You You can't
any I don't want to get any any deeper
than I am, but yeah, you you
>> I'm not trying to dig you. No, that's
that's good. So,
he started badmouthing me to other
prisoners. And I knew he was bad
mouthing me, okay? But I'm thinking, got
to be patient. Figure out how I'm going
to get my revenge on this guy. But, you
know, you can't make it obvious. You
can't just go up and and pound him,
>> right?
>> You have to do like with Wallace.
>> So, in the meantime, there was a serial
killer in the unit who we called truck
because he was a long-distance truck
driver. And he used to drive cross
country and he loved toes. So he'd pick
them up and have sex with them in the
cab of his truck, but he didn't want to
pay them, so he would strangle them. And
he strangled one and thought she was
dead and threw her out of the truck, but
she lived
>> and she was able to identify him.
>> So they knew that he was the serial
killer, but they couldn't prove it. So
only the only thing they got him on was
kidnapping, assault, you know, whatever.
So he got 20 years. Did the
>> for the one girl.
>> For the one girl. Did the whole 20. But
like I say, the cops knew that he was
the serial killer because as soon as he
was incarcerated, the killings stopped.
>> Mhm.
>> So they set up this plan to trap him.
and
they sent a a parole officer to his
house to do um an inspection, a a
surprise inspection. They found a gun in
the house. Truck attacked the the PO. He
ended up getting another 20. So, he was
doing the second 20 when I met him. Hey
yay.
>> For reasons that were never clear to me,
this guy constantly sought my approval.
I don't know why. Like he would say
stuff like, "Oh my god." He said one
time, "You were with the agency? I was
with the agency." Guy had like two
teeth, right? And they were little black
nubs. You know, you were with the
agency. I I was with the agency. I said,
"Yeah, good for you." He said, "Yeah, I
ran a shrimp boat down to Angola to
supply arms to the to the rebels." I go,
"In a shrimp boat across the Atlantic
Ocean." Yeah, you stick with that story.
So, I would just I was like openly rude
to him, but I didn't realize he was a
serial killer. One of the Italians said,
"You know, be careful of him. He's nuts.
He killed a lot of people."
>> Yeah. So, so I backed off with my
attitude toward him, but he would say
things like, "Hey, uh, John, there's a
new classic rock station at uh 1580 a.m.
I know you like classic rock." I'm like,
"Thanks, Truck. Hey, John. I I saved a
seat for you uh if you want to watch the
football game." Oh, thanks, Truck. And
I'd sit down. So, I'm sitting next to
him one day
and as close as I am to you, that's how
close we were to the email computers.
There's a prison email system. It's not
really internet. You can't have internet
in prison, but you can send an email,
>> right?
>> And Cat in the Hat is standing there.
That morning, I had been called to the
lieutenant's office because I had an
interview request from NPR and I had to
sign a release. So, they just say,
"Kiryaku, lieutenants office." Usually
people are called to the lieutenant's
office because they're ratting somebody
out,
>> but I'm not a rat.
>> So I knew why I was called lieutenant's
office. It was to approve the NPR
interview.
So I'm sitting this close to Cat in the
Hat sitting directly next to truck and
Cat in the Hat says, not knowing that
I'm three feet behind him. Cat in the
Hat says, "Do you hear Kiryaku was sent
to the or called to the lieutenant's
office? That guy's a rat, he says. And I
just sat there and truck says, "That guy
just called you a rat."
And I thought, "Here's my opportunity."
And I said, "An hour ago, I heard him
call you a ch
child."
>> Mhm.
>> He didn't say a word. He stood up, walks
over to Cat in the Hat, and beat him to
within an inch of his life.
Everybody runs back to their cells at
the first sign of trouble. Everybody
runs back to the cell cuz they didn't
see anything. Right.
>> Right.
>> They just sat there watching the
football game as he's beating this guy
nearly to death 3 ft away from me.
So next thing you know, you know,
you hear the horn going off. I get up. I
casually walk back to my cell. Then they
have lockdown. Then they have to bring
medics to come and clean up Cat in the
Hats from everywhere. And uh sure
enough, I get called down to the
lieutenant's office
and they're mad cuz they just watched
the security film and I'm just sitting
there watching the football game while
this guy is getting wailed on next to
me.
>> So um
the lieutenant says, "So tell me about
the fight." I said, "There was a fight?"
He said, "Oh, you're going to play it
like that, are you?" I said, "I don't
know what you're talking about. I was
watching a football game and then I
heard the alarm go off." So, I went back
to my to my cell and you didn't see the
fight three three feet away from you. I
said, "I didn't see any fight." I said,
"Maybe you were in a fight, huh? Why
don't you tell me about the fight? What?
You want me to do your job for you now,
too?" He goes, "Get the [__] out of my
office. Admit nothing. Deny everything.
Make counter accusations."
>> I smiled all the way back to my cell.
They got nothing from me. What ended up
happening was I killed two birds with
one stone. Truck received an extra
charge for assault. They added 5 years
onto that 20-year sentence and he was
sent to a medium security prison.
Uh Cat in the Hat had to go to an
outside hospital. He was so severely
beaten. And then after he got out of the
hospital, they sent him to solitary. He
was there for 6 weeks. M.
>> So he came back and people had told him
what happened
and he uh he came back like this and
he's like,
"I'm sorry I said you were a rat. I
should never have said anything like
that." I'm just looking at him and I
said, "Listen, I'm going to tell you
something. If I ever hear my name cross
your lips ever again,
you're dead.
You understand me? and he goes, "Yes."
And I was done with him, too.
>> You owned the Italian mafia persona
>> and you also leveraged your almost a
sociopath, too, right?
>> Almost a sociopath.
>> I mean, I It's appreciable when you tell
the stories cuz you you dislike both
characters.
>> I did.
>> And and justifiably, and one who ends up
with more time, everyone would feel
like, well, he deserved more time.
>> He deserved it. He's a serial killer.
>> It is very brilliant. And it is.
>> Thank you.
>> Tying this all in. That is wonderful. I
love that.
>> Yeah, it is. I'm I'm I'm genuinely not
proud of either one of those stories
that I told you. But
prison's not normal life
and you have to protect yourself. And
that that first day when I realized I
was not going to the camp, I thought,
you know what? You're trained for this.
You've lived in far worse places than
Lorettto, Pennsylvania,
and you are going to remain at the top
of the heap. So, I started with
strategic alliances. That was rule
number one. Establish strategic
alliances. My strongest one was with the
Italians, but I was good with the
Aryans, too. And the other ones had no
problem with me. So, I didn't need to
make problems where they didn't exist.
>> I mean, I think it was brilliant. And it
is very true that you have to completely
become a different person. It's almost
like being drafted or something and
being sent to Vietnam. I mean, if that's
not in your character, then you better
figure out how to make it in your
character. That's right.
>> Because that's the life you're about to
live.
>> Mhm.
>> How much of the now that you're long
been out and got to experience some of
the racial division? I know it wasn't a
high security or anything, but
>> Right. I know guys that are that have
been in high security prisons that that
are fights every day and they literally
can't get to the email box to even
communicate because they're locked down.
They're
>> basically in solitary.
>> Yes.
>> And a lot of it's racially motivated,
gang motivated, all that stuff.
>> Like 90% of it is racial.
>> So how how does how are those people
specifically affected when they go back
out? because I
>> That's a great question and it's an
important question because we do nothing
literally nothing to prepare these
people for life on the outside. So if
you if you're in a maximum security
penitentiary or a medium which is also
violent it
>> and dangerous
>> um
>> and then they just open the door and let
you go.
>> What are you going to do? First of all,
you've been hardened inside. You now
tend toward violence because that's how
you've been settling everything since
you went in.
>> You have no new skills in many cases you
don't know how to read and write. And
you go back to do the only thing that
you knew how to do, which in most cases
was to sell drugs. And then you go back
to the old neighborhood.
>> And you also separate yourself from
other cultures because you were made to
live
>> segregated.
>> Yeah. So you live 15 years inside where
you hate the blacks or you hate the
Mexicans or whatever and then you get
out and are supposed to acclimate.
>> How do you do it? I say in the book that
one of the real shocks for me in the
beginning was
how racially and ethnically divided it
was. It was like walking into 1950s
American South where everything was
segregated. So take the cafeteria as an
example.
You have this cafeteria and imagine a
dividing line right down the middle. One
half of it 100% black.
Every black prisoner is on the right
side of the cafeteria. The left side is
everybody else, but they're subdivided.
So the first
I'm going to say table. It's actually
three tables put together. So the first
row is the Aryans and it it it's
graduated. So the actual
Aryan Brotherhood are at one end and the
so-called good guys, white guys who were
not rats or to are on the other end.
Okay. The second table on the one end is
all the Italians and next to them are
all the Native Americans,
right? And then behind them, all the
rows are the rats and the child.
So everybody's divided.
And the Hispanics just sit with the rats
and ch I never understood that. They
they they don't care what you're in for.
They just assume it's drugs. Sometimes
it's drugs and child crimes and they
don't care. Would it be more functional
if everyone were like that or do you
still think that's a bad idea? I'm and
I'm just it just come to mind when you
bring it up. It's almost like you either
buy into the segregation or you or you
don't.
>> Right.
>> And it would be difficult to separate
people by crime cuz even on the inside
it's difficult to tell who's innocent
and who's not. I know you found some
obviously innocent people or people that
were screwed over.
>> Yeah.
>> But that would be difficult to do that
because everybody was charged.
>> Mhm. Is it even possible or would it be
a better idea if everybody were just
like, "Hey, let's make the best
experience out of this." I mean, it
seems impractical.
>> That would be the best, but not at all
practical.
>> And there's such hatred at play, you
know, people and and then biases and
hatreds are reinforced while you're
there, too. you know, seeing these two
guys just scrap it out where one is in
the end laying unconscious on the floor
because he had the audacity
to change the channel on the TV.
It It's just stunning to me.
>> Stunning. So, what what is prison reform
look like to you having had that
experience and knowing that at the state
level it's probably worse?
>> I mean, it just it doesn't get better.
So,
>> that's right. So, what does prison
reform look like? You've got people that
go in and try to teach and mentor, but
it's all the well- behaved, but
sometimes you can't be well behaved
unless you've got the intellect and and
sophistication for trickery that you do.
>> Yeah. Well, just as background, the
United States has roughly 5% of the
world's population. Okay. And we have
25% of the world's prison population. We
are so over regulated, overcriminalized
in this country that according to to um
the book Dr. Harvey Silverglate, author
of the book Three Felonies a Day, that
the average American on the average day
going about his normal business commits
three felonies. I've written a couple of
times about Congress over the last 20
years has created 50 new crimes every
year for the last 20 years. 50 new
crime. It's a thousand new felonies that
last year you could do no problem. This
year it's a felony
>> and they don't purge either. They don't
>> purge. I mean they just keep stuff on
the books.
>> Yeah. You spit in the wind on Saturdays,
it's a felony in Vermont.
>> They could leverage it if they needed
to. Almost keep it
>> back. And that and that's my that's my
point is that if they want to get you,
they're going to get you and there's
nothing you can do to protect yourself.
So number one is toptobottom
re-evaluation of the criminal code. I I
I write about this stuff all the time.
I'll give you another example. This one
still makes me angry. There was a woman
in Honolulu who was an employee of the
Department of Commerce, National Oceanic
and Atmospheric Administration, Noah.
They're the weather people. They They
belong to the Department of Commerce.
So, Honolulu is very expensive. She's a
GS12 mid-level nobody. So, she and a
business partner buy a boat and on the
weekends they take tourists out to go
whale watching. One weekend they're out
there and they see an orca, a pot of
orcas, and one of the orcas is eating a
seal. So everybody runs to the side of
the boat and they're taking pictures and
somebody goes
to the orca. I don't know to get him to
stay near the top like the orca is going
to say, "Oh, somebody is watching me and
taking a picture."
>> Yeah. Idiot human response.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Couple of weeks later,
FBI,
she answers the door. Uh, you have a
boat? Yes. You take tourists out on the
boat? Yes. Were you out there two weeks
ago? Yes.
see the uh orca eating a seal. Yeah. Did
you whistle at the at the whale? She
said, "No, somebody did." You know what
she says? I I video all the the trips
and I sell the DVDs to the tourists. Do
you want me to look? They take all the
DVDs. Couple of weeks later, they come.
They arrest her. They take all the DVDs.
They take her computers. They take her
phone. They take everything. They
confiscate the boat. and they charge her
with one felony count of interfering
with the feeding of a wild animal, which
is a violation of the Endangered Species
Act.
Okay.
She said, "I didn't whistle at the
whale. Somebody else did."
>> Right.
>> Well, they couldn't figure out. It was
unclear on the video. They arrest her.
She fought this thing for five years.
In the end,
they bump it down to a misdemeanor. She
does a year of probation. She pays a
fine. But she was fired from her job.
She lost her pension. She lost her boat.
She lost her condo. Her business
relationship broke up. She had to start
back at square one. So I ask, is society
safer because they went after her?
>> Yeah. Are you and I better off in
society because they protected us from
this woman who may or may not have
whistled at a whale.
>> But this is what we're up against.
>> This isn't illegal in any other country
in the world.
>> Why would it be illegal here?
>> It's difficult sometimes to get a
legitimate case called in to that the
FBI will adopt.
>> May I give you an example there,
>> please?
May of 2020,
CO has just started. I get a job offer
to be the chief operating officer of a
of an Athens, Greece-based investment
company. It's a job from heaven, right?
I negotiate a package, I take the job, I
start flying back and forth every two
weeks. Washington, Athens. Washington,
Athens. I'm loving it.
>> Yeah. I'm there about 6 weeks
and I call my lawyer who's one of my
best friends. He's uh the former deputy
attorney general under President Reagan
and I said he said, "Hey, how's it going
out there?" I said, "Bruce, you're not
going to believe this whole thing is
just an elaborate bank fraud."
He said, "I I got to resign, but I'm not
sure what to do." He said, "Download
every document you can download onto a
thumb drive and quit." So I download 15
20,000 pages of documents prove
largecale
bank fraud. I quit. I come back to DC.
So I call the FBI. I just can't get
through. There's an FBI agent in my
neighborhood. I said, "What do I what do
I do with this?" And he said, "You got
to call 311." I said, "That's what you
call to fill the potholes." He said, "I
know, but you know, we got the system
now. You call 311, they say, "Oh, refer
it to the police. The police are going
to realize that it's federal. Then they
bump it up to us and then if we're
interested." I said, "Forget that. I'm
not going to waste my time doing that."
So, I called my lawyer again and I said,
"You remember this guy,
>> Ben? He used to be the deputy director
of the FBI." He said, "Yeah." I said, "I
used to be in touch with him regularly.
Are you still in touch with him?" He
said, "Sure, I'll call him." He calls
Ben. Ben says, "I'll get you into the
FBI. So he makes us an appointment at
the Washington field office. I take my
thumb drive. My lawyer and I go to the
Washington field office. We sit down
with this agent and I said, "I have
documentary proof of a largecale
international bank fraud scheme." And
the guy puts up his hands and he goes,
"Guys,
if this doesn't have the words
terrorism, China, or January 6th, we're
not interested."
>> And that was the end of it.
as if they're just underst staffed.
>> But all those processes are so jacked up
anyway because you're you're also these
days you're also banking on the fact
that somebody that answers 311 isn't
lazy, sends it to a police department
detective who isn't lazy, who then calls
an FBI agent who isn't lazy.
>> I mean, all those things are never going
to fall in a row anyway. Nope.
>> I've had stuff on local levels and
federal levels that I try to hand people
and I'll I'll do I'll write the PC for
you.
>> Same here.
>> I'm I'll do the work. I was so angry
that I flew, my lawyer and I on our own
dime flew to Athens and we met with the
Greek uh police fraud unit and then we
flew to Israel from there because there
was an Israeli component to this and we
met with the Israeli police and they're
like, "Yeah, we'll take it."
>> Yeah,
>> that's that's
>> outrageous. So that's number one is
there are just too many people in prison
because we have too many crimes on the
books and sentences are draconian. You
know for example
a life sentence
in Europe means 17 years.
We'll we'll sentence people to a
thousand years and they'll they'll do it
until their you know bones are turning
to dust, right? Um,
but
>> that's all relative. I mean, a sentence
should be a sentence and that's
>> kind of is that not part of the problem,
too? I mean, you you get sentenced to 20
years and they say, "Hey, in the feds
you're going to do all 20, which is not
necessarily the case either, but close
enough. I mean, 20 should be 20
>> and if there's an extenduating
circumstance that you can appeal, then
great, you get out earlier, but
>> or even a mitigating circumstance." And
there's but you also have all this
discernment on each judge who's sent in
from a different political party. And
>> look at Texas for example. 85%
of the death penalty sentences in Texas
are from Harris County. Just Harris
County.
>> Wow.
>> How's that How's that fair?
>> Yeah. These poor Houstononians.
>> Exactly.
Don't commit murder in Houston.
>> Yeah.
>> You're going to get executed.
>> So, anyway,
sentences are too long. We have too many
laws. Not not too many laws. We have too
many crimes. Um, and probably the most
important part here, well, we don't have
we don't have uh parole uh in the
federal system. Right.
>> Right. There there's a little bit 15%
good behavior, but that's it. If you're
if you're sentenced to 20, you're going
to do 20 or close to 20. Mhm.
>> Um but in 1979 in the Carter
administration, we started phasing out
educational programs and then by the
time we were midway through the Reagan
administration, they were gone. Time was
you could learn, you know, plumbing,
electrical work, small engine repair,
whatever, correspondence course, and get
a college degree.
That's all gone. The only things that
are available to you are a GED course
and a preGED course and that's it.
>> Yeah, it's all.
>> And the the more distinct uh the more
prestigious, should I say, leadership
programs and stuff like that are only
for people with certain sentences. If
you're going to be short stage, you
don't get it. If you're forever stage,
you don't get it.
>> Then you have to qualify and get all
these things. They make it jump through
so many hoops. seems.
>> But you're right. And then those people
get out. It's worse for us.
>> It's worse for us as a society
>> because they're going to they're going
to they're going to reaffend.
Recidivism is over 50%.
And it's even more in poorer
communities. That makes us less safe.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, you would think that it would
be better for us, better for society if
we teach these guys
how to unclog a drain or something.
something a skill that they can get a
license for that a
>> felony being not prohibitive.
>> Exactly.
>> Which is another
>> we're not asking that they be made
airline pilots.
>> Right.
>> Right. Let them become plumbers.
>> They don't work at a bank. But
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah. And there's there are so many
problems, but you think that's at the at
the root. You think the the criminal
system and laws on the books need to be
>> Yeah.
>> re-evaluated. And I would also say
another problem,
let me let me rephrase.
Dr. Peter Moscows, 30-year Baltimore
detective, is now a professor of
criminal justice at John J. College of
Criminal Justice in New York. He wrote a
book called In Defense of Flogging,
which is tongue-in-cheek. It's he
doesn't really defend flogging. Um
but he says that the prison systems as
they are today in America whether at the
federal or the state levels are nothing
more than
employment agencies for otherwise
unemployable
rural white men.
Almost all the prisons in America are in
rural areas surrounded by farmland. They
are the only industry in these areas. So
if you just got out of the military,
you're not going to find a job in, you
know, in Lorettto, Pennsylvania,
population 1,200.
The prison's there and they're always
hiring.
Or if you are a flunky from the local
police academy, you just couldn't cut it
and the police academy, the Bureau of
Prisons is happy to take you. The only
qualifications to be a prison guard are
you have to have a GED or be working on
a GED and no felony convictions. That's
it. I I say in the book too, one of them
things that surprised me
>> when I went to prison was mail call,
right? They have mail call six days a
week and often times a prisoner would do
the mail call. Prisoners aren't allowed
to do the mail call, but they would do
it regularly. Why? Because the guard who
was supposed to do mail call can't read.
>> Oh lord.
>> He just can't read. And so he just has
the you know whoever is standing nearest
to him. Why don't you just do it?
>> Yeah. And and part of that is
circumstantial though too because if you
try to put it in the heart of a city and
see if they'll approve that zoning.
>> Can you imagine?
>> No.
>> It's not going to happen. It'll never
happen.
>> No, they're always going to put you in
the state.
>> Always.
>> But that's that's an interesting
consequence of that of that circumstance
is that then you're just going to get
kind of the lowest common denominator to
oversee this.
>> That's right.
>> And you you the problem the other
problem is you can't throw more money at
the prisons.
>> No.
>> And we are already
>> you can't
>> throwing money at
>> the Bureau of Prisons is the largest
bureau inside the Justice Department. It
has the biggest budget
>> bigger than the FBI inside the Justice
Department.
>> Yeah. Practically wasted, too. The
squandering money half the time.
>> Oh my god. Yes.
>> He's bring Elon in, I guess, and put him
in a prison and see what he comes up
with.
>> Yeah.
So, uh I'm curious, too. So, and this
may kind of bridge some of this gap. How
how long were, and I am tying this back
to the prison thing too, but how long
were typically your undercover
operations when you go out and work on a
case, were there intermittent breaks and
flying back home or whatever? Okay. And
and during So, what was an average
length or what was an extraordinary
length of of operational time that you
spent out? It
>> it varied widely. So
it could be as short as one meeting to,
you know, pass a document, to collect a
document, or, you know, to determine if
this guy is the real McCoy or not. It
could be just as short as that one day.
>> Mhm.
>> Or it could go for years,
>> right? And it seems like the years
similar to the prison experience, which
is what I'm trying to get at, would be
an interesting thing to mentally
reconcile because even you are stating
that your personality became someone
else in prison.
>> That's exactly right.
>> And your personality obviously is
somebody else when you're doing these
CIA ops, whether they're longer or
shorter, especially the longer ones. How
do you reconcile that and come back? And
I'm not trying to be all movieesque cuz
you know I have some experience doing
some of that too.
>> Yeah.
>> But there is some reality to it. It's
>> Oh yeah man. You have to be in the right
mental frame
>> right. So
>> to be able to do this.
>> Yeah. So how do you how do you come back
though because there has to be some
degree of struggle and reaclimation and
>> it's all about preparation.
>> Okay.
>> Um as as a general rule I don't talk to
people on planes. That's from my agency
days where I have to get in character so
to speak. Oftentimes I would be crossing
borders or transiting airports in a in a
with a false passport from a different
country. So, you know, rule number one,
don't draw attention to yourself, right?
So, I just don't talk to people on
planes.
And I was flying one time from Milan
to a to a country in Eastern Europe and
I'm sitting next to this big fat Italian
guy and ba
never shut his mouth the whole trip. And
I'm giving him one-word answers to get
him to stop. He's like, "Well, what do
you do for a living?" I said, "Um,
involved in import export." "But what do
you uh what do you import and export?" I
said, "Uh, whatever. Whatever I can make
money on changes all the time." Uh,
well, like like what? Give me an
example.
Finally, I said, "All right, look. I I
smuggle women and cigarettes from
Eastern Europe, okay? Are you happy
now?" And he goes, "I don't think I
approve." I said, "I didn't ask for your
approval, so shut the up." And then he
just sat there like this the rest of the
flight.
But he kind of threw me off.
>> Mhm.
>> And then I had to start all over again.
And then you get to the place where
you're going to do the meeting. You
usually get there a day in advance. And
then you have to slip into whatever your
cover is. Maybe you do some window
shopping. Maybe you go to a hunting
lodge. You know, maybe you go to a rare
book seller because you're an expert in
rare books that day or that week or
whatever the operation calls for. And
then you have to sort of settle back
into your cover. Cover is very, very
important. You have to live it. And it
has to be backstopped. So it's not just
John, you know, arrives in this country
and is a dealer in rare books. John's
got to have a business card that says
he's a dealer in rare books. And when
somebody calls the number on it, it
rings at the CIA and they say, you know,
Acme Rarebrooks, may I help you?
>> So, I can't have some Italian guy
throwing me off my game on the plane,
>> right?
>> And and in doing so for a long period of
time,
>> Yeah. Did you ever find yourself
acting out of character when you
returned in? whether it would be, you
know, a post-prison experience or
>> once I was so paranoid about
surveillance. I was in Williamsburg,
Virginia, and this car had been behind
me for a couple of miles, and I'm
stopped at a red light, and I don't
know, I I got it into my head that this
that I was under surveillance, and I was
preparing to just crash through the cars
in front of me to escape. And then I'm
like, "Wait a minute. What are you
doing? This is Williamsburg.
>> You can't do that either.
>> What are you doing? And I just told
myself to relax. I got off at the first
exit. There was a barbecue restaurant
there and I just stopped and had a Diet
Coke and just sat there and tried to
calm down.
>> What about your relationships? Does it
affect your relationships adversely?
>> That's the most important question. I
think the CIA has the highest divorce
rate of any entity in government. It's
it the last number that I saw was 78%.
Oh
>> jeez.
>> And um and I'm divorced twice.
You
>> And you attribute it to those
experiences.
>> Uh my first time my first my first
marriage definitely.
>> That was the the Greek the Yeah. So we
told that story in in the first one.
>> She had had enough.
>> Yeah.
>> It's enough of this,
>> you know,
>> it was less about your character and
more about what you did and just the
fact that it was such an unstable way to
live, right?
>> Yeah. It it really was. And then you
have little kids. Our our kids were like
six and three at the time. And you know,
I'm I'm dragging an an assassination
squad home with me to, you know, kill
me. And when they realize they can't,
then they kill the next door neighbor.
And my wife is like, "Enough."
>> Yeah.
>> We're going home.
>> Yeah. Understood. Um, you had mentioned
one time, and I'm sorry that I can't
figure out where I heard this, but I
know I heard it before you deny it, but
you had made a comment one time about,
you know, most CIA folks, and it may
have even been here before we were
rolling last time, but most CIA people
when you talk about being on the verge
of sociopaths, but this and this and
this, they're they're all well intended.
They're they're good people. They're
great at what they do. You know, there's
all and you said flippantly, you know,
there's always the 1% that just want to
go kill people.
>> Yes.
>> I'm curious about if there's a place for
those people.
>> How does that work? They they they knock
they they assassins specifically or how
does that work within those confines?
>> The CIA has two different organizations.
One is called uh the special activities
division.
Special activities division. Uh before
911 they were homegrown officers. Post
911 they are guys who have just gotten
out of the SEALs, Delta Force, the
Rangers. Um
and then there is a mirror organization
special activities group that's in the
counterterrorist center. And so their
job is to take delivery of the names of
people identified in the Tuesday morning
uh meetings at the White House. These
people pose an imminent threat to the
United States. A clear and present
danger is the terminology that's used
and their job is to go out and
neutralize those threats
>> and all that stuff. Well, I think I know
the answer, but obviously you you've
hinted at the Tuesday morning
>> briefings, so they're not always
substantiated. Oh, no, no, no, no. In
fact, intelligence is notoriously
unreliable.
You listen, maybe maybe I borrowed
$1,000 from you. You and I live in the
same village, right, in Afghanistan. I
borrowed $1,000 from you. and you came
back to me and you say, "Look, you
borrowed $1,000 from me and you haven't
paid anything back. I need my money
back." Instead, I call the Americans and
I say, "He's al-Qaeda."
They put you on the list and then they
kill you and then I don't have to pay
back the $1,000.
It's as simple as that. I wonder you did
good in prison.
So, uh I am curious because when you
mentioned Brennan and I know we've had
some touch point on that where there was
those I mean I would be interested to
know how much you can expound on that
who who are involved. Is that something
that is a recurring thing amongst CIA
directors or is it a is it a
>> Well, this was a story that was broken
by the Boston Globe in 2009. John
Brennan at the time was the deputy
national security adviser for
counterterrorism and he was reportedly
hosting these meetings at the National
Security Council every Tuesday morning
where they would come up with a list of
people to be that week. people who for
whatever reason were deemed to be a a
clear and present danger.
>> And this is with how many people do you
think? And
>> oh, probably fewer than half a dozen.
>> Okay. You would think the smaller number
the better because of
>> the sensitivity
>> compartmentalization. Yeah. You don't
want this out there for the whole world
to see.
>> But it got discovered.
>> It was discovered. Yeah.
>> Was it somebody from the inside that
spoke?
>> It had to be. It must have been because
if you know what and let me let me
qualify that. It was probably somebody
from the White House who objected to it.
Uh
because they're not polygraphed over
there and they are at the agency. Plus
the agency, you got a lot of true
believers. If you're if you're going to
be involved in something like this, it's
because you believe in the mission,
>> right?
>> And so my guess is it probably came from
the NSC. They leaked it. And then, you
know, finally the administration's like,
"Look, these people want to blow us up.
So, yeah, there's a there's a meeting on
Tuesdays. Yeah, we come up with a list,
you know, to stop them from killing
you." So,
>> and I thought I found it interesting
because as a kid,
>> um I'm close to your age, so you know,
the Iran Contra stuff, the the hostages
and and all that kind of stuff was also
fascinating as as it was with you.
>> Me, too. And I always thought it was
just I guess as a kid you think it's
cool but it's also you know when you
gain you know political awareness.
It seemed like and I could be wrong the
70s and 80s had a lot more of that. Oh
we're having this issue with this new
president over here and then all of a
sudden be like where did the SEAL team
go? Oh there they are. Oh that guy was
assassinated. It just seemed like that
happened more often. I don't know if
it's a communication deal where
everybody has to know everything and
it's almost swung the pendulum the other
way, but within the clandestine
services, it seems like you're saying
that that is still a practice and that
goes on and and despite the fact that we
think we know so much about what's going
on.
>> Yeah. The CIA changed dramatically on
911. I I used to work for a deputy
director named Jim Pavitt who had this
mantra. He would repeat it all the time
that the job of the CIA was to recruit
spies to steal secrets and to analyze
those secrets to allow the policy makers
to make the best informed policy.
Period. Recruit spies to steal secrets.
Post 911, it became a paramilitary
organization.
And so a lot of the mission changed to
be to stop the threat.
>> Mhm. You know, certainly you've got
longer term, more sophisticated
operations going on against the Chinese,
the Russians, the Iranians, whatever,
the North Koreans.
But in terms of dayto-day operations to
protect Americans, it was these teams of
guys from special forces going out and
just doing things that people don't
normally talk about.
>> It changed I think that's what changed
the FBI's focus, too. When you talk
about, hey, it's not about terrorism. I
mean,
>> that's right. That wasn't a primary
focus leading up to that.
>> It wasn't. It really wasn't.
>> Very much internal focus, right?
>> That's right.
>> Well, that I mean, I guess that's good
and bad, but when you were talking about
uh some of those if you have somebody
that's crooked that's running those
meetings and sharing intel as if it's
been vetted.
>> Well, let me ask you a question. Do you
remember
at the very end of the Obama
administration? So we're talking about
2016,
Eric Holder, the attorney general,
testifying before the Senate Armed
Services Committee, and Senator Ran Paul
is asking him, "Does the president have
the authority to murder an American
citizen on US soil?"
Well, Senator, we've never had a
situation like That's not what I'm
asking you. As the attorney general,
does the president have the authority to
murder an American citizen on US soil
without benefit of a trial?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So, what happens then if there's
somebody at the National Security
Council who draws up a list that
includes, you know, Abdullah, Muhammad,
Rashid, and Tegan because I don't like
you. I don't like your politics. I put
you on the list. Who's going to stop
him? Who's going to even know that there
is a list? Right?
>> I mean, do we just trust that these guys
are going to do the right thing?
>> And it certainly isn't going to to end
up that I get offed and there's some
kind of a a righteous case to follow.
>> No. Exactly.
>> You're coming off a list like that, you
got every protection.
>> Exactly. And then the CIA goes into
court and says, "National security, your
honor, and the judge says, "Case
dismissed." which happens all the time,
right?
>> So, obviously, it's not a good idea, and
I appreciate that it's not a good idea.
When I was 10 years old, I thought it
was cool.
>> I did, too.
>> I told my parents when I was nine, I
wanted to be a spy.
>> Yeah.
>> And I told them when I was 16, I wanted
to be a spy in the Middle East.
>> Yeah. Well, part of that is lunacy, but
>> Yeah.
>> My dad is like, "Can't you be a
dentist?"
>> So appreciable. I I love it. I have
something interesting I'd like to do and
we'll see how this turns out because who
knows I may have some names on here that
turn into something something else a
complete left turn but I put together um
I have I have a handful of questions
that were left over from the last time
that are kind of random. Um so I don't
want to go into too many left turns but
this this might cause some left turns
anyway. I have a word association, okay,
that I like to play. And I have some
names and uh if you have a word or a
phrase to describe the first thing that
comes to mind or something interesting
you want to elaborate on, but I'll start
with just some these are super random
and in no order probably on purpose, but
Dick Cheney. Oh,
>> first thing that comes
>> dangerous.
>> Dangerous
short explanation.
>> Dick Cheney pushed the bounds of the
Constitution more than any other vice
president in American history. And we've
learned now a generation after he left
office that he really was the president.
He had primacy over foreign affairs,
intelligence, defense, energy,
everything that mattered. George W.
Bush, who by all accounts was a
perfectly lovely man, just simply was
not in charge of the country. Dick
Cheney was.
>> And that is that due to his personality
cuz I know George George's personality
was passive and cool and yeah,
everything's okay.
>> The movie Vice uh has kind of a funny uh
scene where Bush is trying to convince
Cheney to run for vice president and
Cheney says, "No, no, I don't want to do
it. No, I'm not interested." No. Okay.
Well, I would have to be in charge of
foreign policy. Bush says, "Done." Uh,
defense policy. Okay. Intelligence. All
right. Energy. Yes. Trade. Okay.
Okay. Then I'll do it. I'll do it. And
then he does it. And Bush just turns it
all over.
>> Remarkable position to be everyone
looking this way while this is happening
over here. It's kind of a whole vice
president thing.
>> All right. How about uh Bill Clinton?
>> Disinterested.
Bill Clinton famously uh was briefed by
the CIA twice in his eight years as
president. He had no interest whatsoever
in intelligence. Al Gore had a great
interest and Gore was briefed six days a
week for eight years. And if there was
something important that Clinton needed
to know, Gore would brief him. But Jim
Wolsey, who was uh Clinton's first CIA
director, said that um he had never
briefed Clinton and he wasn't sure
Clinton would recognize him in a
meeting. Huh.
>> Mhm.
Well,
>> he trusted Gore that much.
>> He did. He did. And Gore really was on
top of things.
>> Uh this is going to be a weird one. And
tell me if you know anything about this
cuz I don't remember exactly when your
CIA stint started, but Kiki Camarena.
>> No. Well, he's kind of a famous uh
>> kind of a famous DEA agent who was
killed um in fact, I think he was the
first one that was killed uh in Mexico
by one of the cartels. And it was the
death of Kiki Camarina that led the
Reagan administration to pursue
legislation that would allow US law
enforcement to kidnap people overseas
and clandestinely bring them back to
face trial. So part of that whole story
was about
and this you know there's no distinct
story because all this stuff was
obviously under cloud of suspicion but
that he was on to the CIA for moving
arms Nicaraguan contra arms and that the
CIA had some role in having him taken
care of.
>> Entirely possible. Have you seen the TV
series Snowfall?
Uh, I have not seen it.
>> It used to be on like FX or AMC. Now
it's on uh Hulu.
>> Um, it is, in my view, the definitive
account of the CIA's role in the
movement of cocaine from Latin America
to Los Angeles in the 1980s. It's
incredible.
>> And that that was a man and there's so
many um questions answered. Yeah. That
that get brought up too about how that
happened. Um,
we already talked about John Brennan.
Yeah, that's one. We won't go. Let's
Let's go. Um, I have not a not a desire
to go super deep here, but I may have a
question for you
>> regarding Jeffrey Epstein.
>> Mhm.
>> I know you've been saturated with all
that stuff.
>> Yeah, it's been busy.
>> Are you one of the people that that feel
like he may have been recruited?
>> Oh, by the Israelis. Yeah.
>> So,
>> strongly. I believe it strongly. So I
have I have my question to you is this
because you you would know more than any
barring a name on that list which I can
only imagine that there has to be a name
on that list that is so significant that
something would come crashing down.
Otherwise,
would it not be a good idea to if you
know that somebody has something that
they're blackmailing you over and you
know that it's you're just biting your
time by sitting on it, you can change
the timing of everything that happens by
just exposing it yourself. Rip the
band-aid off,
>> right? I mean, that's the logical thing
to do.
>> It's it's a it's going to be terrible.
Yeah.
>> But it's on our timing. On our timing,
not on someone else's. That's right.
>> Okay,
>> I agree 100%.
100%. Just be done with it. And remember
the lesson of Watergate. It's not even
the crime that brings down presidents.
It's the cover up of the crime that
brings down presidents. Watergate was a
second rate burglary. A bunch of idiots,
former CIA officers, CIA contractors.
They they burgle the DNC headquarters at
the Watergate Hotel and they get caught.
Mhm.
>> But then when the White House denies and
denies and denies and denies that they
were involved, it was that cover up that
led to the one and only resignation of a
president in American history.
>> Remarkable.
>> Yeah. And a wide suspicion cuz then you
wonder how many parts are
>> How deep does this go?
>> Yeah.
>> US military dominance.
>> Yeah. I I don't believe that we're so
dominant.
you know, the the the
method of warfare, the standard of
warfare is changing very quickly. We're
seeing it on the battlefield in Ukraine
right now, for example, where where it's
it's Black Mirror. It's drones and these
robot dogs that scare the hell out of
me. And and we're getting to the point
where where drones are going to be the
future of warfare, or maybe they're the
present of warfare. But, you know, we've
always struggled. We the the United
States have always struggled with things
like um
urban warfare. We're not good at it. We
haven't figured it out. Uh and and
long-term pacification and nation
building. We're not good at it. And one
of the things that we have consistently
missed from a policy perspective is that
when we go in to a country to liberate
it, we are never seen as liberators.
We're seen as invaders. and occupiers,
>> right? Only in our own minds are we
doing what we feel like is in the best
interest of other people.
>> I told you in the last uh the last time
we spoke that
the night before the invasion of Iraq, I
was the notetaker in a meeting. It was a
principal committee meeting. So, it was
supposed to be chaired by the president,
but it wasn't. It was chaired by the
vice president. And it's all in they're
all in a bank of monitors. So, it's the
vice president, Condisa Rice, the the uh
National Security Adviser, Colin Powell,
uh General Tommy Franks from Sentcom,
um
a bunch of guys from the National
Security Council, and George Tennant.
So, I'm sitting directly behind George,
and I'm taking notes, and Cheney starts
the meeting by saying, "General Franks,
why don't you start by giving us the
order of battle?" I've said before, I
hate order of battle briefings. I hate
them. They mean nothing to me. And he
says, "Well, the elements of the first
cavalry are moving here and we're 10
clicks from this village and the second
mountain brigade is I don't care where
these guys are. Just go fight your war
the way you want to fight it and we
don't need to know where each guy is
moving on the map."
So then Cheney says, "So everything's in
place for tomorrow." And Frank says,
"If everything goes as planned, we can
be in Tehran by August."
And then George discreetly turns off his
microphone and he goes, "Did he say
Thran or did he say Baghdad?"
And I said, "He said Tehran."
And George goes, "These people lost
their minds."
And then he turns the microphone back on
and just sits there. So, we go through
the rest of the briefing and one of
these idiots from the National Security
Council, I never like this guy. He used
to say something. He used to call
Kurdistan Kurdland,
which was offensive. And then I saw an
unnamed White House official said, you
know, Kurdland, blah, blah, blah. And I
said, he's the source for the Washington
Post because he's the only person in
town who says Kurdland.
>> You just outed yourself.
>> Yeah. So anyway, he says, "The moment we
cross that border tomorrow, they're
going to throw flowers at us."
So the meeting ended and uh I went back
to the deputy director's office and he
said, "How was the meeting?" And I said,
"Did you know we were going to invade
Iran?"
And he said, "Are they still talking
about that? We're not going to invade
Iran." I said, "So and so said they're
going to throw flowers at us when we
cross the border tomorrow." I said, 'Do
these guys know nothing about history.
And he said, 'N no, they know nothing
about history and they know nothing
about the Middle East.
>> How do we get better intel? I mean, even
today, we're looking at similar
circumstances in the Middle East where
we just assume like, well, this is what
we think is a great idea, therefore
everyone else thinks it's a great idea.
>> Yeah. The Iranian regime is a house of
cards and as soon as we drop these
bunker busters, people are going to take
to the streets and overthrow the I told
us, "No, they're not." I'll tell you, my
girlfriend is is Iranian,
and she goes to Iran two or three times
a year, and she sends me like every
night she'll send me uh videos. People
are out at 1:00 in the morning at the
cafe, and there's music, and people are
laughing and and enjoying each other's
company.
That government's not going anywhere.
Their economy lacks for nothing because
they have such great trade relations
with Russia, China, and India. We have
crippling sanctions on them. Well, guess
what? They can get everything they need
from the other guys.
>> Mhm.
>> And so the notion that this country is
just going to fall apart as soon as we
launch an air strike, that's fantasy
land. It's not going to happen.
>> Yeah. And it I just don't know where you
find somebody cuz everybody's going to
have their idea of someone reputable who
knows from the inside.
>> You know, somebody asked me the other
day, "Well, what about the the Shaw of
Iran in exile?" And I go, "The guy in
Maryland?" I said, "No, he's not going
to become the new Shaw of Iran. No,
never going to happen."
It seems like we're missing, you know,
kind of part of the premise of even this
show is really finding strings of
commonality between people.
Could you tell me maybe a couple
examples of cuz I think that would solve
this problem too if you had somebody who
had actual cultural experience over
there to explain how people are going to
take it as opposed to a political stance
put out by the government.
>> Absolutely. But could you give me a
couple examples of maybe somebody uh a
terrorist or a prisoner or somebody like
that who has a lot more in common with
us common folk than most people would
would wonder why.
Yeah, I can give you a couple. I talk
about this guy in my very first book. He
was the first indepth interrogation I
did when I got to Pakistan as the chief
of counterterrorism operations. He was a
Jordanian and we captured him coming
across the border from Tora Bora. So the
guy is cuffed and he's chained to an
eyebolt in the table and I've never done
an interrogation before. We didn't have
interrogation classes at the CIA. The
FBI normally did interrogations, but
this was different. So I sat down and
I'm thinking, should I be like a good
cop? Should I be a bad cop? And I said,
"Ah, screw it. I'm just going to have a
conversation with the guy. Neither good
nor bad. just gonna ask him. So I
introduced myself. I don't think I use
my real name. And um I said, "Is your
name, you know, Ahmed Ahmed?" And he
said, "Yes, it is." And I said, "Uh"
I said, "So what were you doing in Tora?
You're Jordanian. Why were you in Tora?"
And he said, "Well, for a couple of
reasons. Number one, uh I went to
Afghanistan in 2000 to open an orphanage
for for u parentless Afghan children.
And you know, the Arabs were very
involved in Afghanistan and al-Qaeda
approached me and I joined al-Qaeda. I
said, "You joined al-Qaeda?" And he
said, "Yes." I said,
>> like a left turn.
>> Why'd you do that?
>> Yeah. And he said, 'Well, they were very
generous in funding the uh the
orphanage, and they didn't ask anything
of me. He said, I I never had a weapon
or anything, but I'm an Arab living in a
non-Arab country, and they came to me
and, you know, asked for help and they
would bring children to the orphanage
and blah blah blah.
Like, okay. And I laid out a map on the
table and I said, "One of the things
that we're interested in is the the path
that you took from Tora Bora across the
mountains into Pakistan." We used to
call them rat lines, right? So we wanted
to plug up the rat lines. These
mountains are prohibitive.
>> They're so steep and jagged and it's
almost impossible to you can't go over
the mountains. You have to go through
these valleys. So
>> the map was very specific. So I said, '
Show me how you got from Tora Bora to
Qua, Pakistan. And he laid it all out.
And he would say, 'Well, there's a
village right here and there was a guy
in the village who had a Toyota pickup
truck and he drove me from point A to
point B. His wife gave me some food and
then I spent the night in a barn, you
know, here or a hvel, whatever it was.
He couldn't have been any more detailed.
I knew he was telling the truth. I knew
it because we already knew the rat
lines.
>> Yeah.
>> We just wanted to see if he would
>> You're making up a story. You're not
going to be overly detailed. You're
going to be underdetailed.
>> Exactly.
And I said, "Um,
one last question." I said,
"Why would you tell me all this? I know
you're telling the truth. Why would you
tell me all this?" And he goes, "I'm
your prisoner. what good would it do for
me to lie to you?
And I said, "Okay." And then he says,
"But now I have a question for you." I
said, "All right." And he says, "I would
like to invite you into the embrace of
Islam and I will be your godfather."
And I said, "Well, thank you for that."
I said, "I'm a Christian and
I'm going to remain a Christian, but
thank you for the offer. I appreciate
it."
We ended up releasing him back to
Jordan. He wasn't a combatant. He just
kind of got caught up in everything and
came across the border with all the
other al-Qaeda people. But there were
lots of people like him. Um, one of the
things that I heard many, many times,
and usually it was it was from the lower
level, the younger, you know, kids 18,
19, 20 years old was
they didn't know anything about the
United States. They didn't know anything
about American foreign policy. They were
in these isolated villages. Uh, and they
couldn't read and write. They had no job
skills. And they wanted to get married.
You're 18 years old. You want to get
married in that culture?
>> That's what you're thinking about. And
here too.
>> Here. But what man wants his daughter to
marry this kid who can't read and write,
can't work, you know, doesn't have any
skills?
So, they can't find a bride. The local
imam would go up to them and say, "What
are you doing in this village? you don't
want to stay in this village, you should
go to Afghanistan, make jihad against
the Americans, and if you do that, we'll
give you $300 a month. And if you're
martyed, will give your parents a $500
martyrdom bonus. And they're like,
"Okay."
And they just go.
But that's that's got to be an
extraordinarily different culture to
take that on. Because you could take a
poor American all day long and say
you're gonna still pay him a little bit.
Yeah. Go fight the rest or take care of
your family, which is seeing far outside
of yourself, which I think so many of us
are.
>> But this is the role of Islam,
>> right? It's
they they genuinely believe that there
is something waiting for them in
paradise. And so they'll they'll make
the best of what they have here. And if
it doesn't work out, h then they go to
heaven anyway. So what's the difference?
>> Yeah, but Christians are going to go to
heaven anyways, too. You're not going to
see a lot of them. Well, you know the
old the old joke that uh Osama bin Laden
went to uh he he was he was killed and
he he went to heaven and George
Washington was waiting for him and
George Washington beat him up, punched
him in the face, gave him a black eye
and then next to George Washington here
comes Thomas Jefferson and Jefferson
beats him up and punches him and gives
him the second black eye and then
Alexander Hamilton, you know, kicks him
in the balls and beats him up and
finally he says to God, "What's going on
here. And God says, "You idiot. I told
you 70 Virginiaians, not 70 virgins."
>> I love it.
Of course. And we need some more jokes,
too. I can still screw word association.
What do you think is I mean, you you
have an extraordinary life. You've had
ups and downs and experiences that most
of us can only dream to have. What do
you think is your
most accomplish your your greatest
accomplishment essentially? What do you
think?
>> Oh yeah. I blowing the whistle on the
torture program.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. I wouldn't have said that 10 years
ago. 10 years ago I may have even said
that I wished I had kept my mouth shut
because I lost literally everything. I
lost my job. I lost my pension. I lost
my family, my marriage. I lost
>> everything.
But, you know, in retrospect,
John McCain, uh, 6 weeks before I got
out of prison, I called my wife. I was
able to call her for 15 minutes every
other day. And I called her this one day
in December, and I said, "How was your
day?" She said, "It was great." I said,
"Yeah, why was it so great?" And she
said, "Because the Senate torture report
came out today, and it proved that
everything you said was true." And John
McCain got up on the floor of the Senate
and said that the country owed me a debt
of gratitude because if I had not said
something, they would never have known
what the government was doing in their
name. And then when the McCain Feinstein
amendment was passed, McCain credited me
with spurring it on. And it outlawed
torture permanently in the United
States.
>> And so that's
>> something I can be proud of.
>> Well, you should be proud of that. I
find it that's remarkable though too
because you've also turned that
>> tragedy into something. You turned a
tragedy into another tragedy because the
the program in itself is a tragedy.
>> Tragedy.
>> Oh, but and by doing that that's a
really surprising answer, but I think
it's truly appreciable. I think it's
fantastic. I mean, you must be in a much
better headsp space now.
>> Much better. Much much better. It's all
>> you really get to know who your friends
are in in a situation like this and and
the the answers would surprise you.
>> The answers would surprise me. What are
what do you
>> like the people that you think are the
least likely to walk away
>> are the first ones?
>> Yeah.
>> Is it is it because they have is it just
a
I don't know. I guess there's a
discernment between what is the mission?
I mean, you're talking about, hey, we're
willing to do things that are unethical
pretty much
>> for the cause.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, they're just on the other side
of that line where you say, this is the
unethical thing. I was willing to secret
even if I don't believe in it because
we're part of something bigger and
you're saying this is this crossed a
line where
>> it is sociopathic.
>> It is right and it's illegal. It's
criminal. You know, the day after I blew
the whistle, I got an email from a
retired deputy director of the CIA,
deputy director. And he said, "You've
chosen a difficult road. I only wish
that I had had the guts to do it
myself." And I saved it as a souvenir
to remind myself that I had done the
right thing.
>> Yeah.
>> And then, you know, I I had I had agency
friends. I had one guy. He actually came
to my door to my front door. I hadn't
seen him in years. And he said, "I just
wanted to tell you I think you did a a
brave thing. It was the right thing to
do, but you have to understand that I
can never speak to you again." And I
said, "I I get it. We all choose our
paths in life."
>> Yeah. There's no balls to that, though.
>> Yeah. No, no, he's a coward. But at
least he realizes, recognizes that he's
a coward.
>> A transparent coward.
>> But I think a lot of people would feel
that way. And and it was just
>> I also feel like I think we touched on
this last time. I also feel like people
underappreciate how
the emotional level that we were all on
during 911
>> where you know when you talk about you
know we just made this list and we went
out and these people I think everybody
was in support of that.
>> Yeah. Everybody was
>> you know they've come to our turf and
attacked us and everybody thousand
Americans in one day.
>> Yeah. So I think the the people that
either didn't live through that time who
were younger
or have just lived through periods of
time and people even talk about co like
I can't believe we did whatever but you
know there was a year where nobody knew
what the hell we're supposed to do.
>> Yeah. We didn't know any better.
>> Yeah. So you know hindsight is 2020 and
when you look back on that it's easier
to to dismiss the level of pure emotion
that I think everybody shared here.
>> That's right. I agree. So, I can I can
see where the the program came into
play, but it also needed to be like
we're also freaking professionals one
>> and we are humans with ethical standards
too. And that's right.
>> So, I I appreciate too that you've
you've carved that lane and reminded us
it was there for the
>> in the first place.
>> It was it was there in the first place.
The law was clear.
>> Was illegal,
>> right? For a reason. for a reason. We
executed Japanese soldiers in in 1945
for watching American PS. That was a
death penalty offense to watch somebody.
The law never changed. So, how was it
like magic? It was it was legal in 2002.
We should just go ahead and do it. I
actually do it 187 times to Khalik
Muhammad, 83 times to uh Abu Zuba.
And do you think that So when you first
blew the whistle, you didn't you weren't
even aware of the extent?
>> No, no, I was not aware of the extent. I
I'm glad you brought that up. Um I said
in my original ABC News interview that
we had watched beta one time and the
reason why I said that is that that was
what was reported back from the secret
site. They were even lying internally.
They said, "Oh, we him one time. Look,
he opened up. He gave us all this great
intelligence. No, he didn't. First of
all, you stole that intelligence from
the FBI report
>> cuz they got the information from him
just by having a conversation.
>> And then youeded him 83 times and lied
about that, too.
>> So,
>> well,
>> we didn't even know that until, well,
the inspector general wrote a report
about it in 2005 and the report was
declassified in 2009. So, we didn't even
know about it until 2009. And there was
some degree of regret that you had, I
think, in the beginning.
>> Oh, yeah. I looked like a fool.
>> But because you were standing alone,
>> but I think over time it it had to have
reinforced, especially when they came
out with hell, I didn't even know the
the
barely the tip of it was even what I was
reporting on.
>> Even internally, they were lying to each
other.
>> And conspiracies are so hard to hold.
>> So, it's pretty incredible. I mean, this
has finally come out, but it's years and
years later that people are even willing
to buy it. You still have people that
that are still angry about it. Uh, you
got the Epstein thing that's all
conspiratorial.
>> You you went through the uh I don't
remember which prince it was. You had
the Saudi prince situation where they
had the the numbers that would have
potentially exonerated Abu Zabeda, which
which was your prisoner that ended up
again
>> being imprisoned in up. I spoke with his
attorney again last week and uh he lost
his appeal in the ninth the ninth
circuit court of appeals, but the ninth
circuit
um pointed out that
the reason they ruled against him, he
had sued the two contract psychologists
that him. They said that the contract
psychologist,
yes, had broken the law by toring him,
but the torture had been authorized by
the CIA and so the psychologist can fall
back on um national security defense and
so they dismissed the charges. But one
of the things that the court wrote was
that the CIA for the very first time
confirmed that they had him Right. They
just at first they denied and then they
just ignored. Now they say, "Okay, okay,
weed him and that the had been approved
by the president
>> just as I said
>> in 2007
>> and everybody's like traitor."
>> Yeah.
>> And they still do. Like I said, there's
only so much people are are willing to
to look at factually or otherwise. It's
so politicized now
>> that it just seems difficult to to
fathom that there's some kind of a list
somewhere or there's a number of people
who are aware of those circumstances
that that stuff isn't going to get out
in a legitimate way. I mean having a
hidden source that I can't reveal told
me blah blah blah I mean that all that's
going to do is stir the pot.
>> Mhm. But if somebody has something
tangible
and all those things were available and
you had people that could have stood up
for you and said, "Nah, this is this is
correct."
>> Mhm.
>> It would have been I can't imagine where
your life would be now.
>> It'd be completely different. I would
say
>> it would be better or worse, though.
>> Better.
>> Do you think?
>> Yeah. I wouldn't have had to stand alone
like that.
>> But don't you think that made you I
mean, we learn the most from our worst
experiences, unless we die, of course.
>> That's a good point. I think that that's
the things that you've that you've
persevered through now knowing what you
did. I mean,
>> this would this would no way that would
be your greatest accomplishment first of
all,
>> right? Cuz it would have been watered
down.
>> Yep. It would have it would have been
the blip.
>> It would have been the blip.
>> So, I think it's I think it's
extraordinary. I like I said, I I'm I'm
a big fan. I really appreciate all of
your time every time.
>> No, I appreciate it. These are good
conversations we have. I enjoy them very
much. and anything I can do for you, let
me know.
>> Thank you very much.
>> I will actively look for opportunities.
So,
>> I appreciate it.
>> Just let me know what you need, man.
>> Good to see you.
>> What's it take? What you going to do?
What you going to do? Success around
the second grade rules.
A confident fake to make you do make you
do what they want when they won't pay
the pool.
A diplomatic be is the one to see you
through.
Don't let those [__] take you off
your game or just to let him loose. Sit
here in the front seat. Baby, ain't that
sweet? And take a little honey from the
money be. But don't be the fool.
[Music]
Political magical potion. A missing
piece at the end of the game. A slow
roll. See the truth in soul motion. I
never found in 63 like
shine a truth lies between blurry lines.
If you're going to call me back,